<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"
    xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
    xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
    <channel>
        <title>ashmod.dev</title>
        <link>https://www.ashmod.dev/blog</link>
        <description>Blog posts from ashmod.dev</description>
        <language>en</language>
        <lastBuildDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 00:12:46 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://www.ashmod.dev/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
        
    <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s talk about AI</title>
        <link>https://www.ashmod.dev/blog/ai</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.ashmod.dev/blog/ai</guid>
        <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
        <description><![CDATA[Addressing the elephant in the room.]]></description>
        <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>AI is the hot topic these days, a good few believe it&#39;s a &quot;bubble&quot; and others are convinced it&#39;s a drop-in replacement for search engines.
I believe it&#39;s neither.</p>
<p>But I do believe it&#39;s the next big thing.</p>
<h2>A look back on other &quot;big things&quot;</h2>
<p>Big things are always around, &quot;hype&quot; over new technology has been around for a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/History_of_technology">really long time</a>.</p>
<p>I grew up around the time the internet was becoming mainstream. Websites were popping up everywhere, it was the hot topic. I&#39;m certain there&#39;s a good few back then who thought the internet was a bubble, and that it would never really replace traditional forms of media. That didn&#39;t really age well.</p>
<p>I also remember when mobile phones started to become popular. Well, this one is tricky, since mobile phones had been around for a while, in really different forms. But when smartphones showed up, it was a game changer for a lot, mostly for tech savvys at first, but eventually for everyone. </p>
<p>Then came social media, then streaming platforms, ...</p>
<p>We are always looking for the next big thing, it&#39;s in our nature. And big things usually do come around, sooner or later.</p>
<h2>Why AI then?</h2>
<p>Like most previous big things, AI is not really new. It&#39;s been around for decades, but only recently it has become accessible to the masses. Sound familiar? </p>
<p>AI, however, has been growing in availability and usability at an unprecedented rate. ChatGPT was officially released in late 2022, I&#39;m writing this in late 2025, it&#39;s been 3 years. In that time, ChatGPT jumped from a conversational bot to a full fledged multimodal agentic system, capable of doing pretty much everything. </p>
<p>This rate of growth is new to say the least. Mobile phones, internet, they all took their sweet time to get to that &quot;mainstream&quot; spot. AI is already there. It&#39;s been there for a while, and that, while seemingly exciting, is a little terrifying.</p>
<h2>The elephant in the room</h2>
<p>AI is here to stay. It&#39;s not going away, and it&#39;s not a bubble. It&#39;s the next big thing.
And this is, in layman&#39;s terms, really bad.</p>
<p>To understand why this is bad, let&#39;s take a look at the impact of each previous big thing, and yes, order matters.</p>
<p>I believe telephones were the trend at some point, they made communication easier, accessible and faster. While this sounds dreamy, it also caused people to not be as close anymore. It doesn&#39;t sound that horrible, but it&#39;s a start.</p>
<p>The internet made information accessible to everyone, it made communication even easier, and it made the world much smaller. But it also made <em>all information accessible</em>, to <em>everyone</em>. One could argue that this is not a huge problem since mainly adults and professionals were using it. Bear with me here.</p>
<p>Smart phones made communication, and internet, much easier, and much more accessible. Now everyone could just grab their phone and get online, anytime, anywhere. Internet access no longer required a public library or a home computer. And this is where things started to get really bad.</p>
<p>Social media is the cherry on top of this whole mess. Not only we had easily accessible information and misinformation, we now have platforms built on that premise; accessing information is no longer passive.</p>
<p>This trend of disastrous impacts should give you a pretty good idea of what I&#39;m hinting at here. I don&#39;t believe any of the next big things would be &quot;as bad&quot; as the one before it. Simply because, every new big thing is the accumulation of all previous big things, their good, their bad, and their really bad.</p>
<h2>Is it over?</h2>
<p>While we&#39;re tripling our carbon footprint every few weeks, using water at crazy rates, building massive data centers, consuming components and making it more difficult for the average user to keep up. We&#39;re not <em>entirely</em> doomed yet.</p>
<p>Don&#39;t get me wrong, I don&#39;t hate AI. In fact, I&#39;ve been a really early supporter of it. I used to be really interested in old NLP models: Siri, Alexa, Cortana, Google Now, you name it. I was fascinated by the idea of talking to a machine, and having it follow up. This is probably why I was also really interested in most video games. I later became interested in learning more about machine learning, deep learning, discovering and reading all about the architectures that were coming out. This was all theory, then came LLMs.</p>
<p>I&#39;m a bit torn on LLMs, I love them, I think they&#39;re great. But a little too much of a good thing can be bad. LLMs are great for helping with tasks, routine work, brainstorming ideas. But they should never be a replacement for you. Your brain. </p>
<p>Your brain is the most powerful system to ever exist. It&#39;s the definition of general intelligence. It&#39;s what any AI is trying to mimic. But it simply can&#39;t. Not yet, and likely never. </p>
<p>They&#39;re called &quot;co-pilots&quot; for a reason. We shouldn&#39;t let them replace education, critical thinking, and creativity. Because if we do, we&#39;ll be effectively devolving as humans. </p>
<p>One of my all time favorite quotes that pretty much sums all this up is author <a href="https://x.com/AuthorJMac">@AuthorJMac</a>&#39;s tweet:</p>
<p><img src="/content/blog/ai/jmactweet.png" alt="Tweet by Author J Mac on AI"></p>
]]></content:encoded>
        <category>AI</category>
        <category>thoughts</category>
        <category>history</category>
    </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
