<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"
    xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
    xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
    <channel>
        <title>ashmod.dev</title>
        <link>https://www.ashmod.dev/blog</link>
        <description>Blog posts from ashmod.dev</description>
        <language>en</language>
        <lastBuildDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 10:37:39 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://www.ashmod.dev/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
        
    <item>
        <title>Your brain is lying to you. (And that&apos;s good.)</title>
        <link>https://www.ashmod.dev/blog/brain</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.ashmod.dev/blog/brain</guid>
        <pubDate>Sat, 31 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
        <description><![CDATA[You’re living in a brain-made simulation.]]></description>
        <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>You believe you&#39;re seeing reality. Making rational decisions. Controlling your life. But the fact is, your brain is <em>constantly</em> lying to you. And that&#39;s a good thing.</p>
<h2>Your &quot;Reality&quot; is a guessing game</h2>
<p>Your brain doesn’t work like a camera.</p>
<p>It doesn’t record reality and play it back. It predicts what’s out there, based on past experience, incomplete sensory data, and a lot of shortcuts.</p>
<p>Light hits your eyes.
Sound hits your ears.
And then your brain fills in the rest.</p>
<p>Colors? Not really “out there.”
They’re interpretations.</p>
<p>Objects? Your brain stitches edges together and decides what counts as a thing.</p>
<p>Even the smooth feeling of time flowing forward? That’s a construction too.</p>
<p>Your ancestors didn’t need perfect accuracy. They needed fast guesses.
Is that a snake or a stick?
Friend or threat?</p>
<p>Hesitation was expensive.</p>
<figure class="image-with-caption">
  <img src="/content/blog/brain/fraser.png" alt="Fraser Spiral Illusion">
  <figcaption><b>The Fraser Spiral Illusion:</b> At first glance, you'd think this is an image of a spiral pattern, but that's not the case. The brain sees incomplete data and automatically predicts a pattern that isn't there. True image is a series of concentric circles.</figcaption>
</figure>

<h2>Dreams prove the point</h2>
<p>I&#39;ve always found dreams really fascinating. Every night, your brain runs a full simulation with zero external input.</p>
<p>No light.
No sound.
No real body movement.</p>
<p>And yet... you see. You hear. You feel fear, joy, embarrassment. You talk to people who aren’t there. It all feels <em>real</em>.</p>
<p>Apparently, our brains don&#39;t need the outside world to create a convincing one. It&#39;s all about patterns..</p>
  <div
    class="themed-svg"
    role="img"
    aria-label="Dreams visual"
    style="
      --themed-svg-url: url('/content/blog/brain/dreams.svg');
      --themed-svg-aspect: 2816.07 / 732.97;
    "
  ></div>

<p>Dreams are what happens when our brain goes offline from reality and keeps doing what it does best: predictions, storytelling, and emotion.</p>
<p>Walking life is the same thing, just with live data plugged in.</p>
<h2>Feelings run the show</h2>
<p>We like to think we&#39;re logical creatures. We&#39;re not.</p>
<p>We&#39;re emotional systems that occassionally do math. Your brain uses feelings as shortcuts. Good or bad. Safe or risky. Familiar or strange. Logic usually comes later, if all.</p>
<p>That’s why dreams stick with you emotionally even when they make no sense.
The plot doesn’t matter. The feeling does.</p>
<p>Your brain cares about what matters, not what’s tidy.
This is a pivotal point for the way brains are wired, from our early age. But this is a topic for another time.</p>
<h2>You think you&#39;re in control. You&#39;re mostly not.</h2>
<p>&quot;Decision-making&quot; is hoax. A lot of decisions start before you&#39;re consciously aware of them. Your brain commits, then your conscious mind shows up to explain why it &quot;chose&quot; that option.</p>
<p>One of my favorite manifestations of this is the fact that if you&#39;re deciding between two things, and toss a coin, you&#39;ll actually make your decision before the coin lands. The coin flip is merely a spur.</p>
  <div
    class="themed-svg"
    role="img"
    aria-label="Coin toss visual"
    style="
      --themed-svg-url: url('/content/blog/brain/toss.svg');
      --themed-svg-aspect: 1981.12 / 802.93;
    "
  ></div>

<p>Many such cases;
You feel hungry <em>after</em> your body decides it needs food.
You reach for your phone <em>before</em> you notice boredom.
You say something, then you instantly justify it for yourself.</p>
<p>This is more helpful than you think, imagine if you had to consciously approve every tiny action before doing it. You&#39;d never get anything done.</p>
<h2>Your brain wasn&#39;t built for this world</h2>
<p>All of these tricks evolved in a slow, small, social environment.</p>
<p>Not infinite scrolling.
Not constant notifications.
Not global comparison with millions of strangers.</p>
<p>Your brain is still running old software:</p>
<ul>
<li>Attention locks onto novelty and threat</li>
<li>Social rejection feels like physical pain</li>
<li>Certainty feels better than nuance</li>
</ul>
<p>Modern life pushes all the wrong buttons, all the time.</p>
<h2>So why is this actually good?</h2>
<p>Because the same system that bends reality also gives you <strong>imagination</strong>, it gives you <strong>creativity</strong>, it gives you <strong>empathy</strong>. It gives you the ability to <strong>learn</strong>, <strong>adapt</strong>, and <strong>invent</strong> futures that don’t exist yet. </p>
<p>It&#39;s also the same talented, complex system that comes up with <strong>dreams</strong>, <strong>stories</strong>, <strong>art</strong>, and <strong>science</strong>.</p>
<p>If your brain only showed you cold, objective reality, you wouldn’t be human.
You’d be a sensor.</p>
<p>Understanding that your brain lies doesn’t mean you can turn it off.
It means you can stop blindly trusting every thought, fear, or impulse it throws at you.</p>
<p>You’re not broken.
You’re running a very clever, very old system.</p>
<p>And once you see the illusion, you can work with it instead of against it.</p>
<p>That’s the real upgrade.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
        <category>neuroscience</category>
        <category>thoughts</category>
        <category>consciousness</category>
    </item>
    <item>
        <title>Getting HyperV to coexist with VMs</title>
        <link>https://www.ashmod.dev/blog/windows-hyperv</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.ashmod.dev/blog/windows-hyperv</guid>
        <pubDate>Mon, 29 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
        <description><![CDATA[Scripting a workaround for the Windows virtualization conflict.]]></description>
        <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2>The Calm before the Storm</h2>
<p>It all started on a Sunday afternoon when I, for God knows why, decided to free up space from my Windows C drive.</p>
<p>A bit of needed context first:
I primarily use Windows 10 as my host OS, and I use a Linux VM for development. Additionally, I had a WSL Ubuntu instance on my host, for quick tasks and whatnot.
If you&#39;re not familiar with WSL, that&#39;s <a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/windows/wsl/about">Windows Subsystem for Linux</a>. It&#39;s a system component that allows you to have a Linux VM alongside your host OS, but without having to switch (from boot menu, or to a VM). It&#39;s as convenient as double clicking an icon and, voila! A Linux machine has spawned <em>into</em> your Windows device.</p>
<p>WSL is nothing new, it&#39;s been around for quite some time. In fact, it&#39;s been around long enough that it has undergone a massive do-over around the release of Win11. For a good few years, WSL was running on what is now known as WSL1, the older version that frankly did the job but lacked in a few areas, for example you couldn&#39;t do anything GUI-related with it, or that is heavily dependent on a Linux kernel - because it did not really have one, it used a translation layer to convert Linux system calls into Windows kernel calls, effectively simulating a Linux environment.</p>
<p>WSL2, on the other hand, has a complete Linux kernel. So, it&#39;s essentially a lightweight VM you can run on your Windows machine with no problems. Unless you already run VMs.</p>
<p>So, back to how I wanted to free up space on my C drive. Essentially the problem is, my Ubuntu WSL machine has been living in my C drive taking up a good amount of space. I looked around on how one can move a WSL distro from one drive to another, and found out there is a really simple way to do it:</p>
<pre><code class="language-bash">wsl --manage Ubuntu --move NewDrive:\WSL\Ubuntu
</code></pre>
<p>One tiny problem: This is a WSL2 specific command. I was running WSL1.</p>
<h2>The upgrade</h2>
<p>It was long overdue anyway, so I decided to upgrade my WSL to version 2. Big mistake.
So the first problem was, the machine initially reported an error that it couldn&#39;t upgrade due to missing virtualization dependencies, which makes no sense because I double checked the enabled features and all was good. </p>
<p>I decided to turn the Microsoft Virtualization Platform feature off, reboot (it&#39;s required), then turn it back on, reboot again, and sure enough, it worked. What the hell Microsoft.</p>
<figure class="image-with-caption">
  <img src="https://y.yarn.co/1ab70c93-fce1-460d-8575-3bac5a666e96_text.gif" alt="Roy from The IT Crowd: Have you tried turning it on and off again?">
  <figcaption>Roy from "The IT Crowd" was onto something.</figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Anyway, after a good 2 hours of moving the system, it was time to test it out. Thankfully, it worked (slower, but that was expected since it&#39;s a complete Linux kernel).</p>
<p>One thing I did notice, however, was that upgrading to WSL2 enabled the Windows hypervisor components under the hood (required for its lightweight VM). This, in turn, enforced Virtualization-Based Security (VBS).</p>
<p>This is bad news for two reasons: my existing non-Microsoft VMs might face performance hits, and more importantly, some video games no longer work properly because many kernel-level anti-cheat systems conflict with VBS enabled.</p>
<h2>Windows is a pain</h2>
<p>The fact that there is no way to actually disable VBS (Virtualization-Based Security) still makes no sense to me. Even though there are settings to disable it, they effectively do nothing at all!</p>
<p>I&#39;ve updated settings, policies, and even changed (and created) registry entries. Nothing worked.</p>
<p><img src="/content/blog/windows-hyperv/wisdom.png" alt="XKCD-612: Wisdom Of the Ancients"></p>
<h2>The Script</h2>
<p>I knew the workaround was to toggle the Windows hypervisor off entirely,</p>
<pre><code class="language-bash">bcdedit /set hypervisorlaunchtype off
</code></pre>
<p>This essentially turns hyperV off on the next system boot, giving better VM performance and video game compatibility. But it breaks WSL2, so if you wanted it back you&#39;d have to do:</p>
<pre><code class="language-bash">bcdedit /set hypervisorlaunchtype auto
</code></pre>
<p>It works great, but manually running commands (and remembering the current state) every time I want to switch is a hassle.</p>
<p>So I whipped up this simple batch script to handle the toggle automatically, and check the current status:</p>
<pre><code class="language-bash">@echo off
title HyperVisor Toggle
cls

:: --- admin check ---
net session &gt;nul 2&gt;&amp;1
if %errorLevel% neq 0 (
    echo ========================================================
    echo  ERROR: PERMISSION DENIED
    echo ========================================================
    echo  You must Right-Click this file and choose
    echo  &quot;Run as Administrator&quot; for it to work.
    echo.
    pause
    exit
)

:: --- check current status ---
for /f &quot;tokens=2&quot; %%a in (&#39;bcdedit /enum ^| findstr &quot;hypervisorlaunchtype&quot;&#39;) do set CURRENT_STATUS=%%a

if /i &quot;%CURRENT_STATUS%&quot;==&quot;off&quot; goto :SET_HYPERV_ON
goto :SET_HYPERV_OFF


:SET_HYPERV_ON
    echo ========================================================
    echo   CURRENT STATE: [ HYPERV OFF ]
    echo   (Hypervisor: OFF - Games OK, WSL2 Broken)
    echo ========================================================
    echo.
    set /p CHOICE=&quot;Turn HyperV ON (Enable WSL2)? (Y/N): &quot;
    if /i &quot;%CHOICE%&quot; neq &quot;Y&quot; goto :NO_CHANGE

    :: user said Yes, proceed
    bcdedit /set hypervisorlaunchtype auto
    echo.
    echo [OK] HyperV is now ON.
    goto :FINISH


:SET_HYPERV_OFF
    echo ========================================================
    echo   CURRENT STATE: [ HYPERV ON ]
    echo   (Hypervisor: ON - WSL2 OK, Games Broken)
    echo ========================================================
    echo.
    set /p CHOICE=&quot;Turn HyperV OFF (Enable Games)? (Y/N): &quot;
    if /i &quot;%CHOICE%&quot; neq &quot;Y&quot; goto :NO_CHANGE

    :: User said Yes, proceed
    bcdedit /set hypervisorlaunchtype off
    echo.
    echo [OK] HyperV is now OFF.
    goto :FINISH


:NO_CHANGE
    echo.
    echo No changes made. Exiting...
    timeout /t 3 &gt;nul
    exit


:FINISH
    echo.
    echo ========================================================
    echo   DONE. A RESTART IS REQUIRED.
    echo ========================================================
    set /p REBOOT=&quot;Restart computer now? (Y/N): &quot;
    if /i &quot;%REBOOT%&quot;==&quot;Y&quot; (
        shutdown /r /t 0
    ) else (
        echo Please restart manually later.
        pause
    )
</code></pre>
<p>You can have this script living anywhere as a <code>.bat</code> file and run it whenever you want to toggle HyperV or just check if it&#39;s on or off.</p>
<h2>Wrapping Up</h2>
<p>In the end, this little toggle script has been doing the job for me without having to resort to VBS headaches. Windows virtualization features are definitely powerful, but the conflicts (especially around security like VBS and anti-cheat) can be frustrating. This workaround isn&#39;t perfect; it requires a reboot each time—but it&#39;s simple, reliable, and doesn&#39;t mess with deeper system settings.</p>
<p>If you&#39;re in the same boat, give the script a try. Save it as <code>HyperV-Toggle.bat</code>, right-click &gt; Run as Administrator, and toggle away.</p>
<p>Have a better solution, improvements to the script, or your own horror stories with Hyper-V/WSL2? Drop a comment below, I&#39;d love to hear them!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
        <category>windows</category>
        <category>wsl</category>
        <category>scripting</category>
        <category>virtualization</category>
        <category>vbs</category>
    </item>
    <item>
        <title>Why we judge books by their covers</title>
        <link>https://www.ashmod.dev/blog/good-design</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.ashmod.dev/blog/good-design</guid>
        <pubDate>Thu, 25 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
        <description><![CDATA[Exploring how good design is recognized, and favored by human eyes.]]></description>
        <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Have you ever wondered why most companies do a rebrand every few years, out of the blue, completely unprompted? The design team certainly does not just wake up someday and go, &quot;yeah we should just redesign our identity.&quot;</p>
<p>There must be a reason to it, because humans by nature don&#39;t like change. Unless it&#39;s good.</p>
<p><img src="/content/blog/good-design/chrome.png" alt="Evolution of Google Chrome logos from 2008 skeuomorphic design to modern flat version"></p>
<h2>Why we usually agree on Good Design</h2>
<p>Good design is simple. It&#39;s elegant, and most importantly, it&#39;s relevant. Take a look at Chrome&#39;s early design and what we have now. It&#39;s a drastic change in the span of a decade. But if we were living in a timeline where Chrome&#39;s logo stayed at its 2008 variant, people will not be happy.</p>
<p>The old Chrome logo was bold, shiny, full of 3D effects and metallic glow that screamed &quot;cutting-edge tech&quot; in the era of skeuomorphism. But as design trends shifted toward simpler, minimalist interfaces (think Material Design), that glossy look starts to feel dated. This is why most apps, companies and even plain designs shift to those trends. Because you usually don&#39;t want to be the odd one out.</p>
<p>We accept (and even celebrate) those changes because good design evolves with us. It mirrors cultural shifts, technological advancements, and our changing tastes.</p>
<p>Or, in more american terms:
<img src="/content/blog/good-design/burger.png" alt="Burger King logo before and after 2021 retro rebrand"></p>
<h2>Judging covers</h2>
<p>The phrase &quot;don&#39;t judge a book by its cover&quot; is great advice. Until it isn&#39;t.
Our brains are wired for quick visual judgements, and that&#39;s okay, because usually our brains are right. Humans form first impressions in milliseconds. In a world full of choices, we rely on heuristics to decide what&#39;s actually worth our attention. Color, symmetry, simplicity, and relevance. Good design just taps into this by feeling intuitive and easy on the eyes.</p>
<p>Bad design on the other hand creates friction. Cluttered layouts, mismatched fonts, or outdated styles make us subconsciously think, &quot;This feels cheap.&quot; Even if it really isn&#39;t. </p>
<p>That&#39;s why a beautifully typeset, (literal) book cover makes us assume the story inside is worth reading.</p>
<figure class="image-with-caption">
  <img src="/content/blog/good-design/books.png" alt="Examples of elegant book covers that influence reader perceptions">
  <figcaption>Books I'm judging entirely by cover design and sentenced to my 'maybe later' pile.</figcaption>
</figure>

<h2>Design is everywhere</h2>
<p>Whatever you&#39;re doing in life, you most certainly make design choices everyday. If you&#39;re a writer, fonts, spacing and page design matters. If you&#39;re a developer, clean code matters, UI matters, those promote good Developer Experience, <em>and</em> User Experience. And if you&#39;re the guy behind IKEA, whatever you&#39;re doing is probably good.</p>
<p>The point: design isn&#39;t a separate skill; it&#39;s how we organize intention. And it&#39;s easier to start than you think. Put your thoughts on screen (or paper, or canvas), iterate, and refine. But most importantly, ask yourself: How does it look to <em>you</em>? If you like it, good chance is, everyone else will.</p>
<p>We judge covers because good design isn&#39;t superficial - it&#39;s a shortcut to trust, efficiency, and pleasure. Whether logos, books, UIs, or code, clean symmetry wins because our brains are built to love it.</p>
<p><img src="/content/blog/good-design/twitter.png" alt="Twitter bird logo overlaid with golden ratio geometry"></p>
]]></content:encoded>
        <category>design</category>
        <category>thoughts</category>
    </item>
    <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s talk about AI</title>
        <link>https://www.ashmod.dev/blog/ai</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.ashmod.dev/blog/ai</guid>
        <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
        <description><![CDATA[Addressing the elephant in the room.]]></description>
        <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Artificial Intelligence is the defining topic of our current moment. Some believe it&#39;s a &quot;bubble,&quot; while others think it’s a drop-in replacement for search engines.
I believe it&#39;s neither.</p>
<p>But I do believe it is the next &quot;big thing.&quot;</p>
<h2>A look back on other &quot;big things&quot;</h2>
<p>Technological paradigms are constantly shifting. The &quot;hype&quot; cycle surrounding new technology has existed for a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/History_of_technology">really long time</a>.</p>
<p>I grew up as the internet was becoming mainstream. Websites were popping up everywhere; it was the hot topic. I’m certain there was a  good few back then who thought the internet was a bubble that would never replace traditional media. That didn&#39;t age well.</p>
<p>I also remember when mobile phones began to saturate the market. This one is tricky, as phones had existed in various forms for a while. But when the smartphone arrived, it changed everything - first for the tech-savvys, and eventually for everyone.</p>
<p>Then came social media, streaming platforms, and so on.</p>
<p>We are always looking for the next big thing; it&#39;s in our nature. And sooner or later, those big things usually do come around.</p>
<h2>Why AI?</h2>
<p>Like most previous paradigm shifts, AI is not technically new. It has existed for decades, but only recently has it become accessible to the masses. Sound familiar?</p>
<p>However, AI has grown in availability and usability at an unprecedented rate. ChatGPT was officially released in late 2022; I&#39;m writing this in late 2025. In just three years, it jumped from a conversational bot to a full-fledged multimodal agentic system capable of complex execution.</p>
<p>This rate of growth is unusual, to say the least. Mobile phones and internet took their sweet time to reach that &quot;mainstream&quot; status. AI is already there. It has been there for a while, and that, while seemingly exciting, is also terrifying.</p>
<h2>The elephant in the room</h2>
<p><img src="/content/blog/ai/elephant.png" alt="The elephant in the room">
AI is here to stay. It&#39;s not going away, and it&#39;s not a bubble. It&#39;s the next big thing.
And this is, in layman&#39;s terms, really bad.</p>
<p>To understand why this is bad, let&#39;s take a look at the impact of each previous big thing, and yes, order matters.</p>
<p><strong>Telephones</strong> made communication easier, faster, and more accessible. While this sounds dreamy, it also reduced physical proximity. It wasn&#39;t horrible, but it was a start.</p>
<p><strong>The Internet</strong> made information accessible to everyone. It shrunk the world. However, it made <em>all</em> information accessible to <em>everyone</em>. One could argue this wasn&#39;t a huge problem when the user base was primarily adults and professionals.</p>
<p><strong>Smartphones</strong> made the internet universally accessible. Suddenly, everyone could get online, anytime, anywhere. Access no longer required a public library or a home computer. This is where things became complicated.</p>
<p><strong>Social Media</strong> was the cherry on top. We didn&#39;t just have easily accessible information; we had platforms built on the premise of constant engagement. Accessing information was no longer a passive act.</p>
<p>This trend of compounding impacts should give you an idea of what I&#39;m hinting at. I believe that every new &quot;big thing&quot; is more dangerous than the one before it. Why? Simply because every new technology is the accumulation of all previous ones: their good, their bad, and their ugly.</p>
<h2>Is it over?</h2>
<p>We are tripling our carbon footprint, consuming water at alarming rates, and building massive data centers, all while making it more difficult for the average user to keep up with hardware demands. Yet, we are not <em>entirely</em> doomed.</p>
<p>Don&#39;t get me wrong, I don&#39;t hate AI. In fact, I was an early supporter. I used to be fascinated by early NLP models; Siri, Alexa, Cortana, Google Now, you name it. I loved the idea of talking to a machine and having it understand. This fascination is also probably the reason behind my interest in video games. Later, I dove into the theory of machine learning and deep learning, following new architectures as they emerged, but this was all just theory. Then came LLMs.</p>
<p>I am torn on Large Language Models (LLMs). I love them; I think they&#39;re incredible tools for routine work and brainstorming. But a little too much of a good thing can be bad. LLMs should never be a replacement for you.</p>
<p>Your brain is the most powerful system to ever exist. It&#39;s the definition of general intelligence. It&#39;s what any AI is trying to mimic. But it simply can&#39;t. Not yet, and likely never. </p>
<p>They&#39;re called &quot;co-pilots&quot; for a reason. We shouldn&#39;t let them replace education, critical thinking, and creativity. Because if we do, we&#39;ll be effectively devolving as humans. </p>
<p>One of my all time favorite quotes that pretty much sums all this up is author <a href="https://x.com/AuthorJMac">@AuthorJMac</a>&#39;s tweet:</p>
<p><img src="/content/blog/ai/jmactweet.png" alt="Tweet by Author J Mac on AI"></p>
]]></content:encoded>
        <category>AI</category>
        <category>thoughts</category>
        <category>history</category>
    </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
